Hello, my friends.
And welcome to the complete data structure and algorithms course in this video will start learning on
new data structure on the tree based data structures so that tree a tree is a non-linear hierarchical
data structure that consists of nodes connected by edges.
This is then the tree.
And this is the nodes connected by each other, by the edges.
Other data structures, such as arrays link, it lists Stack and the Q are linear data structures that
stored data sequentially.
While in tree, we will see that it is different in order to perform any operation in a linear data
structure.
That time complexity increase with the increase of data size, but it is not acceptable in today's computational
world.
Different to three data structures allow quicker and easier access of the data as it is non-linear data
structure.
So the three differs from the queue and arrays and linkage lists and arrays and stack with nonlinear
data structure access to that data as it is not a linear data structure.
OK, so this is the ad.
It is the link between any two node and then node is an entity that contains a key or value and pointers
to its child nodes.
So the ball is called nodes, and the link between the nodes is known as edges.
OK.
Now, let's talk about some terminologies.
The Leave.
The last node of each path are called live nodes or external notes that don't contain a pointer or link
to child notes.
So the leaves are that ending notes in turn, the notes that note that have at least a child note is
called internal notes.
So any note that contained and other notes it is known as internal note that it is the topmost note
of a tree.
It's the top of the tree height of a tree.
The height of a tree is the height of the root node or the depths of the deepest note.
So the difference between that note, the upper node, the root and the Leafs, the last leaves.
Depth of A. The depths of inode is the number of edges from the road to the known forest.
A collection of these giant trees is called a forest.
You can create a forest by cutting the root of a tree.
Don't worry, we will see all of these terminologies in the days in next videos and exercises.
Consider this three edge equals to do height equal to do, and that's equal to zero deaths means the
level.
So that took a top route.
The top note is at level zero, the second level is the equal to one depth, equal to one.
And the last note is that's equal to two.
OK.
Creating a tree if I like to create like this tree, but encoding, we need to write some codes.
So how to do that?
What is the algorithm?
What is the syntax behind creating the note?
Or three?
We start by creating nodes exactly like a circular or blanket list.
But here we use left and right.
Despite using next and previous.
OK, so we need to specify the left.
We need to specify the right, and we need to specify the data that is contained.
So if I need to create like the top route node one, then I need to insert the data inside it.
One If I have nodes to the left, I should refer fraud to the left pointer to indicate that that 12
is on the left and nine is to the right and so on.
If I need to have siblings or or children node inside 12, I need to point the left four five.
And there are two there.
Six.
And here we have creating a tree and we know what is that tree?
Now let's move in more complex things like that traversal of the tree, the orders and later on, we
will start creating the codes that responsible for responsible for making and.